Guide to the Corcoran Gallery of Art and Corcoran College of Art + Design, Corcoran Gallery of Art registrar's office records, 1869-2013 COR0005.1.RG
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Corcoran Gallery of Art and Corcoran College of Art + Design, Corcoran Gallery of Art registrar's office records
1869-2013
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Corcoran Gallery of Art
COR0005.1.RG
212 Linear Feet
The Corcoran Gallery of Art Office of the Registrar was responsible for the registering of art objects, handling of loans, shipping and insurance procedures, and controlling the physical inventory and the storage of art objects. This record group contains files and reports generated by the Office of the Registar in the course of their duties. The Accession files provide the most complete record of works entering the Corcoran collection. Material in this record group dates from 1869-2013.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open to research.
When conducting research within The Corcoran Archives collections, please be advised of the following restrictions:
Records of the Board of Trustees (RG 1.0) and records of the Office of the Director (RG 2.0) are closed to research for 25 years from the date of creation.
Development records are closed to research (RG 3.2).
Access to student records is governed by the federal Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA), which protects the privacy of student education records. Student records are closed for the lifetime of the student, and are presumed to be open 75 years after the date of record creation (RG 9.0 Series 4).
Personnel and financial records are closed for 50 years from date of record creation (RG 4.0).
Please see the Public Services and Instruction Librarian for assistance.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Corcoran Institution Board of Trustees donated these records to The George Washington University in 2016.
Arrangement
Organized into 17 series: Accessions [legacy series]; Accessions; Registrar's reports; Loans of works of art [legacy series]; Loan files; Insurance [legacy series]; Insurance files; Reproduction rights and photo orders [legacy series]; Reproduction rights and photo orders; Bequests; Amati and Stradavari instruments [legacy series]; Amati and Stradavari instruments; Miscellaneous subjects [legacy series]; Miscellaneous subjects; Exhibition files; Deaccession files; Collection management files.
Historical narrative
The first section of this history, covering events through 1981, was prepared by Corcoran Archivist Katherine M. Kovocs for publication in 1985 with the support of the National Endowment for the Humanities.
The Registrar's position at the Gallery was established in 1952. The Registrar's duties included the registering of art objects; handling of loans, shipping and insurance procedures; and controlling the physical inventory and the storage of art objects. It was at this time that the Curator's and Registrar's offices, one department until this time, divided into two distinct units.
The 1960s saw a continued increase in the size of the Curatorial/Registrarial staffs as well as greater expertise amongst its members. At various times throughout this decade the curatorial staff featured Chief Curators, Registrars, Curators of Exhibitions, Curator of Collections & Research/Research Curator, Curator of Contemporary Art, Assistant and Associate Curators, and various curatorial and registrar assistants and secretaries.
The 1970s featured further expansion, diversity, and organizational innovations in the Gallery's curatorial and registrar's departments. Until 1975, the Gallery's Director maintained an active role in curatorial affairs (e.g. exhibitions), continuing a trend begun by the Corcoran's first Curator/Director. However, with the appointment for the first time of a Chief Curator, Jane Livingston, in 1975, much of the aesthetic initiative and curatorial administrative responsibilities were placed with the Chief Curator. The Director, now aided by a large, expert curatorial staff, turned his focus toward other Gallery concerns, such as budgets, finances, and fundraising. This is especially true with the appointment of Peter Marzio as Director in 1978.
The latter half of the 1970s witnessed other important occurrences such as the creation of the Associate Director's post, the naming of a Curator of Collections, and the reinstallation of the "American" (permanent) collection.
Persons who figure prominently in the Registrar's Office history include Shelby Cave, Jane (McCall) Cohen, Mary (Hoffman) Porbes, Ellen Gross, Rosemary Jones, Martha Morris, Judy Riley, Glenn Thomas and Susan (Grady) Williams.
The following section of this history was prepared in 2019 by George Washington University SCRC staff with the support of the Luce Foundation.
Following the reinstallation of the "American" permanent collection, the Gallery continued to expand on its American art holdings, beginning to branch out into American contemporary art. In 1979, the Gallery created the post of "Associate Curator of Contemporary Art for the Washington Region." The position was revised later to include a national focus, becoming the Associate Curator of Contemporary Art. With the appointment of Ned Rifken in 1984, the position title was changed again to Curator of Contemporary Art.
Jane Livingston's tenure as the Chief Curator of the Gallery had long lasting effects on the direction of the curatorial department. From 1975 until her resignation in 1989, Livingston placed greater emphasis on photography and progressive modern art. Through her initiative, the Corcoran Gallery became a major force in Contemporary photography. Work by Ned Rifken (Curator of Contemporary Art 1984-1986) and Ed Nygren (Curator of Collections until 1988) further elevated the Corcoran's position in the Washington contemporary art scene.
The Gallery suffered major setbacks in 1989 following the decision to cancel the controversial Robert Mapplethorpe retrospective The Perfect Moment. Jane Livingston resigned in protest of the cancellation, and several members of the curatorial staff followed her in departing the Corcoran. Jane Livingston's position would not be filled for another three years, until the appointment of Jack Cowart in 1992. Cowart then created the position of Curator of Photography and Media Arts in the same year.
In 2007, the Corcoran set out five core subjects for the permanent collections; Historic American Art, Historic European Art, Photography and Media Arts, Decorative Arts, and Contemporary Art. There was a particular focus on the photography and American art collections.
The Gallery continued to acquire art, predominantly photographs and paintings, as well as loan works and house traveling exhibitions until its partition and dissolution in 2014.
Related Materials
Within the Corcoran Archives, several other record groups contain related material to the Registrar's office records:
RG 1.0 Corcoran Board of Trustees meeting minutes and reports -- especially those of the Works of Art Committee -- feature loan and accession information. Annual reports also contain summaries of loan and accession activities.
RG 2.0 Corcoran director's records provide information regarding bequests to the Gallery.
RG 5.0 Curatorial office records contains additional exhibition files.
RG 5.2 Conservation department records include valuable data on individual works of art within condition reports and the quarterly reports of the Conservator.
Scope and Contents
The Registrar's Office Records contain the Corocoran Gallery's object/ accession and deaccession files, as well as additional administrative files, including records of insurance, bequests, reproduction rights, loans of works of art, and exhibitions.
Much of the Registrar's Records before 1950 are bound volumes or "registers." Information on book, bronze, painting and sculpture accessions is located in four accession registers in Series 1.
With the official appointment of a Registrar in the early 1950s, the records of the office become more organized and more complete than those for earlier years. The earlier "registers'' of works of art were no longer used by the late 1940s. Similar accession logbooks were used from then until the early 1960s. After that time, all accession information has been kept on accession sheets in each object file. A logbook of "X" numbers assigned lists those works found during the inventory of the collection during the late 1940s and early 1950s for which there was no notation in any of the registers.
Materials containing information on all other aspects of the Office of the Registrar's activities are either greatly expanded or appear for the first time in this post-1950 period. Registrar's Reports (quarterly), which began in 1959, systematically record the activities of that department for the first time. In addition, reproduction rights and photo order requests make their first appearance in this post-1950 period, beginning in 1963. The volume of loan files expands greatly, providing an informative and complete record of loaned works of art since that time.
Art; Artists; Museums; Washington (D.C.)
- Accessions [legacy series], 1869-1958; Series 1
  Scope and Contents
  The series features four bound volumes, divided by type of work of art, which register accession information:
  1. Register of Bronzes belonging to the CGA (1 vol.) Includes those bronzes, engravings, ceramic ware, electrotype reproductions, medieval armor, etc. acquired by the Corcoran from 1873-1946. The kinds of information contained include accession number; title of work of art; date received; donor name; type of acquisition (e.g. gift, purchase); cost, if applicable; artist name; date work was done; and description or additional comments. The Register is arranged chronologically,
  2. Register of Sculpture Belonging to the CGA (1 vol.) Includes those marbles and casts acquired by the Corcoran from 1869-1942. The Register features information such as accession number; title of work of art; date received; donor name; type of acquisition (e.g. gift, purchase); cost, if applicable; artist name; date work was done; and description or additional comments. The volume also includes an index. The Register is arranged chronologically.
  3. Register of Paintings Belonging to the CGA (1 vol.) Includes those paintings acquired from 1869-1946. Information contained in this volume includes accession number; title of work; date received; donor name; type of acquisition (e.g. gift, purchase); cost, if applicable; artist name; date work was done; and any description or addenda. The volume is arranged chronologically and includes an index.
  4. Register of Books Belonging to the CGA (1 vol.) Includes information on those books acquired from 1873-1951. The volume features such information as accession number; title; author; edition; date received; donor name; type of acquisition (e .g. gift, purchase); cost, if applicable; and any additional comments. The Register is arranged chronologically.
  The Record of Assignment of X Numbers (1 vol.) contains information on those works of art assigned such numbers from 1949 to 1958 (X.1 - X.262). The "X" number signifies that the source and/or date of acquisition are unknown or in doubt. It was meant as a temporary number -- to be removed once a date/source of acquisition has been identified and an accurate, permanent accession number can be assigned. The volume contains such information as date of "X" number assignment, artist name, title of work of art, and the work's final fate-- e.g. final accession number assigned, sale of the piece--and any suppositions on when the work was deposited and by whom.
  Related Materials
  Additional accession materials are located in Series 10 Accessions, 1980-2008.
  - Register of Bronzes, etc. Belonging to the Corcoran Gallery of Art, 1873-1946; Series 1 (Box 133, Volume 1)
    Arrangement
    The Register is arranged chronologically.
    Includes those bronzes, engravings, ceramic ware, electrotype reproductions, medieval armor, etc. acquired by the Corcoran from 1873-1946. The kinds of information contained include accession number; title of work of art; date received; donor name; type of acquisition (e.g. gift, purchase); cost, if applicable; artist name; date work was done; and description or additional comments.
  - Register of Sculpture, etc. Belonging to the Corcoran Gallery of Art, 1869-1942; Series 1 (Box 134, Volume 1)
    Includes those marbles and casts acquired by the Corcoran from 1869-1942. The Register features information such as accession number; title of work of art; date received; donor name; type of acquisition (e.g. gift, purchase); cost, if applicable; artist name; date work was done; and description or additional comments. The volume also includes an index.
  - Register of Paintings, etc. Belonging to the Corcoran Gallery of Art, 1869-1946; Series 1 (Box 135, Volume 1)
    The volume is arranged chronologically and includes an index.
    Includes those paintings acquired from 1869-1946. Information contained in this volume includes accession number; title of work; date received; donor name; type of acquisition (e.g. gift, purchase); cost, if applicable; artist name; date work was done; and any description or addenda.
  - Register of Books Belonging to the Corcoran Gallery of Art, 1873-1951; Series 1 (Box 136, Volume 1)
    Includes information on those books acquired from 1873-1951. The volume features such information as accession number; title; author; edition; date received; donor name; type of acquisition (e .g. gift, purchase); cost, if applicable; and any additional comments. The Register is arranged chronologically.
  - Record: Assignment of "X" Numbers, 1949-1958; Series 1 (Box 25, Ledger 1)
  - Biography of Paintings, 1890-1895; Series 1 (Box 137, Volume 1)
    Information relating to the acquisition and restoration of works of art in the Gallery. Discontinued.
  - Supplementary List of Paintings Acquired or Withdrawn, 1920-1924; Series 1 (Box 137, Folder 2)
    Supplementary list of paintings acquired, or withdrawn, from the permanent collection of the Corcoran Gallery since the publication of the 70th edition of the Catalogue of Paintings, in 1920, until August 1924, together with biographical data concerning painters not included in said catalogue.
  - Index to Record of Paintings Belonging to The Corcoran Gallery of Art, undated; Series 1 (Box 137, Folder 3)
  - Index to Record of Casts Belonging to the Corcoran Gallery of Art, undated; Series 1 (Box 137, Folder 4)
    It is not clear to which volume or register this index corresponds.
  - Catalog of Engravings (Partial), undated; Series 1 (Box 137, Folder 5)
  - Register of Works Received on Exhibition, 1874-1897; Series 1 (Box 144, Ledger 1)
- Accessions, 1980-2008; Series 10
  Additional accession materials are located in Series 1 Accessions [legacy series], 1869-1958.
  This series contains accession files transferred to the Corcoran Archives following the original Corcoran Archives processing project in 1983. Files include duplicate accession sheets, organized by accession number, created in the 1980s, files relating to the Robert A. Lewis Collection, and several acquisition and meeting files of the Museum Board of Overseers.
  - Accession Register, 1961; Series 10 (Box 142, Binder 40)
  - Duplicate accession sheets: Accessions L.X.I.-X.278, circa 1980-1985; Series 10 (Box 84, Folder 1)
  - Duplicate accession sheets: Accessions 69.1-74.71, circa 1980-1985; Series 10 (Box 84, Folder 2)
  - Duplicate accession sheets: Accessions 75.1-85.6, circa 1980-1985; Series 10 (Box 84, Folder 3)
  - Duplicate accession sheets: Accessions 86.1-10.6, circa 1980-1985; Series 10 (Box 84, Folder 4)
  - Duplicate accession sheets: Accessions 11.-25.4, circa 1980-1985; Series 10 (Box 84, Folder 5)
  - Duplicate accession sheets: Accessions 26-26.119, circa 1980-1985; Series 10 (Box 84, Folder 6)
  - Duplicate accession sheets: Accessions 26.120-26.248, circa 1980-1985; Series 10 (Box 84, Folder 7)
  - Duplicate accession sheets: Accessions 26.249-26.795, circa 1980-1985; Series 10 (Box 84, Folder 8)
  - Duplicate accession sheets: Accessions 26.796-39.20, circa 1980-1985; Series 10 (Box 85, Folder 1)
  - Duplicate accession sheets: Accessions 40.1-L.43.71, circa 1980-1985; Series 10 (Box 85, Folder 2)
  - Duplicate accession sheets: Accessions 44.1-49.260, circa 1980-1985; Series 10 (Box 85, Folder 3)
  - Duplicate accession sheets: Accessions 50.1-54.28, circa 1980-1985; Series 10 (Box 85, Folder 4)
  - Duplicate accession sheets: Accessions L.55.1-57.30, circa 1980-1985; Series 10 (Box 85, Folder 5)
  - Duplicate accession sheets: Accessions 58.1-60.41, circa 1980-1985; Series 10 (Box 85, Folder 6)
  - Duplicate accession sheets: Accessions 60.42-64.37.19, circa 1980-1985; Series 10 (Box 85, Folder 7)
  - Duplicate accession sheets: Accessions 64.37.20-68.25, circa 1980-1985; Series 10 (Box 85, Folder 8)
  - Duplicate accession sheets: Accessions 68.26.1-68.26.429, circa 1980-1985; Series 10 (Box 85, Folder 9)
  - Duplicate accession sheets: Accessions 68.26.430-68.26.1038, circa 1980-1985; Series 10 (Box 86, Folder 1)
  - Duplicate accession sheets: Accessions 68.27-1974.98, circa 1980-1985; Series 10 (Box 86, Folder 2)
  - Duplicate accession sheets: Accessions 1975.1-1978.128, circa 1980-1985; Series 10 (Box 86, Folder 3)
  - Duplicate accession sheets: Accessions 1978.129.1-1979.69, circa 1980-1985; Series 10 (Box 86, Folder 4)
  - Duplicate accession sheets: Accessions 1979.70-1982.46, circa 1980-1985; Series 10 (Box 86, Folder 5)
  - Duplicate accession sheets: Accessions 1982.47-1984.30, circa 1980-1985; Series 10 (Box 86, Folder 6)
  - Robert Lewis Collection: Robert Arneson-Ed Guthrie-Part, 1996-2004; Series 10 (Box 111, Binder 1)
  - Robert Lewis Collection: Nancy Hild-Henry Lawson, 1996-2004; Series 10 (Box 111, Binder 2)
  - Robert Lewis Collection: Barry LeDoux - R.A. Miller, 1996-2004; Series 10 (Box 111, Folder 3)
  - Robert Lewis Collection: Nechvatal-Yoshida, 1996-2004; Series 10 (Box 111, Folder 4)
  - Robert Lewis Collection: Appraisals, 1996-2004; Series 10 (Box 111, Folder 5)
  - Robert Lewis Collection: Jonathan's File, 1996-2004; Series 10 (Box 111, Folder 6)
  - Robert Lewis Collection: Not Brought to CGA: Belizaire-Worthington, 1996-2004; Series 10 (Box 111, Folder 8)
  - Robert Lewis Collection: Missing Objects, circa 1995-2008; Series 10 (Box 114, Folder 1)
  - Robert Lewis Collection, circa 1995-2008; Series 10 (Box 114, Folder 2)
  - Robert Lewis Collection: RAL to Cincinatti Art Museum - Correspondence, circa 1995-2008; Series 10 (Box 114, Folder 3)
  - Robert Lewis Collection: Conservation, Correspondence, Receipts, circa 1995-2008; Series 10 (Box 114, Folder 4)
  - Robert Lewis Collection, circa 1995-2008; Series 10 (Box 114, Folders 5-7)
  - Robert Lewis Collection: Box List and Inventory, circa 1995-2008; Series 10 (Box 114, Folder 8)
  - Robert Lewis Collection: Loan Agreements Checklist, circa 1995-2008; Series 10 (Box 114, Folder 9)
  - Robert Lewis Collection: Shipping/Storage, 1995-2002; Series 10 (Box 114, Folder 10)
  - Robert Lewis Collection: Photos and Labels, circa 1995-2008; Series 10 (Box 114, Folder 11)
  - Robert Lewis Collection: Labels, circa 1995-2008; Series 10 (Box 114, Folder 12)
  - Robert Lewis Collection: Photos, circa 1995-2008; Series 10 (Box 114, Folders 13-14)
  - Proposed Acquisitions - Purchases, Gifts, 1998; Series 10 (Box 117, Folder 17)
  - Museum Board of Overseers Reports - Correspondence with Donors, 1999; Series 10 (Box 117, Folder 18)
  - Museum Board of Overseers - Meetings, 1999 April 29-May 10; Series 10 (Box 117, Folder 19)
  - Acquisitions and Loans Committee Meeting, Series 10 (Box 117, Folder 20)
- Registrar's reports, 1959-1980; Series 2
  The reports are arranged alphabetically by type and chronologically within types.
  The series contains reports submitted by the Registrar's Office on an annual (1968-69), bi-monthly (1977-80), and quarterly (1959-72) basis. The bulk of the series is made up of quarterly reports. These contain information on accessions, attendance, docents, exhibitions, insurance claims (beginning in 1965), and loans in and out. The reports also include a special section on the Clark Collection for 1959 and a section on the Corcoran storeroom evacuation project in 1970-71, during which a thorough inventory of the collection was made. In addition, these quarterly reports, like those for the Curatorial Office, contain a Conservator's Report. The Registrar's Reports contain a conservator's section from 1959 to March 1965 and for 1969-70. Beginning in 1971, the Conservator submitted a quarterly report separate from the Registrar's.
  The Registrar's Annual Report for 1968-69 records information such as acquisitions, donors names, loans to other institutions, and travelling exhibitions. The report has been retained because it provides some information which is different from that found in the published Annual Report for that fiscal year.
  The bi-monthly reports feature information, often in statistical form, on acquisitions, insurance claims, loans, reproduction rights, and travelling shows. They appear sporadically for the years 1977-80.
  - Annual Report, 1968-1969; Series 2 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bi-Monthly Report, 1977, 1979-1980; Series 2 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Quarterly Report, 1959 January-1959 March; Series 2 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Quarterly Report, 1959 April-1959 May; Series 2 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Quarterly Report, 1959 June-1959 September; Series 2 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Quarterly Report, 1959 October-1959 December; Series 2 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Quarterly Report, 1960 April-1960 May; Series 2 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Quarterly Report, 1960 June-1960 September; Series 2 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Quarterly Report, 1960 October-1960 December; Series 2 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Quarterly Report, 1961 January-1961 March; Series 2 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Quarterly Report, 1961 April-1961 September; Series 2 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Quarterly Report, 1961 October-1961 December; Series 2 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Quarterly Report, 1962 January-1962 March; Series 2 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Quarterly Report, 1962 April-1962 May; Series 2 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Quarterly Report, 1962 June-1962 September; Series 2 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Quarterly Report, 1962 October-1962 December; Series 2 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Quarterly Report, 1963 January-1963 March; Series 2 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Quarterly Report, 1963 April-1963 May; Series 2 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Quarterly Report, 1963 June-1963 September; Series 2 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Quarterly Report, 1963 October-1963 December; Series 2 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Quarterly Report, 1964 January-1964 March; Series 2 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Quarterly Report, 1964 April-1964 May; Series 2 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Quarterly Report, 1964 June-1964 September; Series 2 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Quarterly Report, 1964 October-1964 December; Series 2 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Quarterly Report, 1965 January-1965 March; Series 2 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Quarterly Report, 1965 April-1965 May; Series 2 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Quarterly Report, 1965 June-1965 September; Series 2 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Quarterly Report, 1965 October-1965 December; Series 2 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Quarterly Report, 1966 January-1966 March; Series 2 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Quarterly Report, 1966 April-1966 May; Series 2 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Quarterly Report, 1966 June-1966 September; Series 2 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Quarterly Report, 1966 October-1966 December; Series 2 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Quarterly Report, 1967 January-1967 March; Series 2 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Quarterly Report, 1967 April-1967 May; Series 2 (Box 1, Folder 34)